Finding Aid for Ladies Literary Club, Ypsilanti, Michigan, Records 1882-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ladies Literary Club, Ypsilanti, Michigan, Records 1882-2008
Ladies Literary Club (Ypsilanti, Mich.)
(in 7 boxes)
6 linear feet
Minutes of meetings, scrapbooks, financial records, reports, and other papers; and photographs.
86323 Bj 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group was first deposited by Mary Leigh Welch, President of the Ladies Literary Club in May of 1943. (Donor No. 2078 ). Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open for research.
The Ladies Literary Club of Ypsilanti (LLC) is an outgrowth of the Ladies Library Association of the same city. At a board meeting of that Association in May of 1878, Mrs. Daniel (Sarah Smith) Putnam proposed the formation of a Literary Club. Mrs. Putnam had recently moved to Ypsilanti from Kalamazoo where she remembered "the effective work and good comradeship in the literary circles of that city and wished for Ypsilanti the same." Soon thereafter, officers were named and an agenda set. The first meeting of the LLC was held June 8 of the same year in the Library Association rooms. Mrs. Putnam was chosen President. The two societies worked closely together over the following years. Many women were members of both organizations. Subsequent meetings were held in members' homes. Later gatherings were held again in the Ladies Library. In 1906, the Red Cross room of the Masonic Temple became the site of the regular meetings. In 1914, the LLC purchased its own building which became its permanent clubhouse.
The initial constitution of the LLC read "The object of this society shall be the mutual improvement of its members through the study of literature, art, science and the vital interests of the day." In the formative years, the focus of the LLC meetings was literary and cultural. Little time was spent on business matters. The first area of study was Africa, its resources and geography, its art and literature. Later attention was paid to European countries and their cultures.
After the incorporation of the LLC with the National Federation of Women's Clubs in January of 1896 and the State Federation of Women's Clubs later that year, the LLC's commitment to public interest began. In that same year, perhaps in an attempt to strengthen the literary and cultural focus of the club, the Women's Study Club was formed as a branch of the LLC.
In 1918 in order to enlarge the focus of the LLC, the following phrase was added to the constitution "(the object of this society is also) to serve as an energizing and uplifting force for all that makes for civic or community betterment." This broadening of the constitution reflects the "usefulness" of the organization and its attempts to shape public policy. How the organization of the LLC evolved is clearly represented in the minutes of the LLC's meetings. Reflecting the constitutional change, the regular meetings became much more concerned with the business of the organization and less concerned with cultural and literary matters.
As the years went on, guest speakers took over the roll of preparing and supplying the lectures at meetings. This role was formerly played by members. In February of 1902, the first guest speaker addressed the Club. Programs began to be more varied. Debates were also held at meetings where both sides of an argument were argued. In February 1912, the first play was staged by the members. This began a yearly tradition. The first mention of an Entertainment and Program Committee can be found in 1899. The first "Music Committee" was listed in a program book of 1908.
A look at some of the Committees which emerged and disappeared over the years affords a glimpse into the interests of this organization. A few of these committees include: "Art", "Education", "Flowers", "Citizenship", "Girl Scout Sponsors", "Sewing"(1943), "War Service-War Bonds"(1944-45), "Sarah George Scholarship", "Health"(1945), "Remembrance"(1957), "Legislation and Conservation"(1964), "City Beautification", "Cook Books"(1974), "Meals on Wheels"(1975).
In 1914, the LLC altered its constitution, incorporated and included in its government a Board of Trustees. These changes allowed the organization to purchase a building which became their permanent clubhouse. Long known in the city as the Grant residence, this Greek revival style house was built in 1840. In 1928, in a celebration honoring the 50th anniversary of the LLC, the mortgage for the property was paid off and in the style of the day, the mortgage papers were "burned with the proper ceremony in the flames of a taper." In 1937,1950 and 1971 large improvements were made to the clubhouse. Over the years, the rooms have been rented out to other clubs for their meetings and gatherings. In October of 1965, the Michigan State Historical Commission presented to the Ladies Literary Building the first historical marker home designation in Ypsilanti. In April of 1971, the building was named to the National Register as the William H. Davis House.
The Sarah George Student Loan fund was established in May, 1928. The Ypsilanti City Federation of Women's Clubs took over the fund from 1930-1938. It was then returned to the LLC and a committee was appointed to oversee its use. With the fund principal growing steadily, the Club decided to change it to a Scholarship fund in 1952. At this time it was stipulated that the recipient of this scholarship must be a girl graduate of Ypsilanti High School attending Eastern Michigan College.
The Ladies Literary Club of Ypsilanti (LLC) Records (1882-2008) documents the development and changes of the activities of the LLC for more than a century. The record group consists of Historical/foundational documents, Regular Meeting Minute Books, Board of Trustees papers, Membership and Program books, Financial Records, Presidents' Files, History of building addition, LLC Magazines, Scrapbooks, and Miscellaneous files.
Subjects:
Arts--Michigan--Ypsilanti--Societies, etc.; Ladies Literary Club (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Women--Michigan--Ypsilanti--Societies and clubs.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ladies Literary Club (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Theatrical productions.; Women--Organizations.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Historical/Foundational documents
  The historical/foundation file includes three booklets which contain the constitutions and bylaws of the LLC. These booklets are dated 1935,1966 and 1980. Earlier constitutions can be found in the Regular Meeting Minute Books for these dates: Sept. 1894, Sept. 1900, June, 1901 and Sept. 1903. Also found in this series are several articles and various speeches from 1896 to 1953 which present an overview of the development of the LLC.
  - Constitutions and bylaws Booklets
    - 1935, 1966, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Histories 1896-1953 (Box 1)
    (consists of articles and speeches, 1896-1953, on the history of the LLC)
- Regular Meeting Minute Books
  The Regular Meeting Minute Books series makes up the bulk of this record group. These handwritten record books document the meetings of the members from 1882 until 2005. Various speeches in the collection allude to the existence of record books from the first meetings which took place in 1878. Unfortunately, the collection as it stands today only encompasses minutes from the meetings of Sept. 1894 and forward to January 1989. Earlier small notebooks from 1882-1890 contain notes about some of the topics discussed at these meetings. They are not however meeting minutes. As the focus of the organization changed so did the format and records of its meetings. In April of 1943, some minutes of the executive board meetings, some treasury reports and some miscellaneous business meetings, began to appear in the same notebooks as the regular meeting minutes.
  - 1882-1885 (Box 1)
    (includes questions to be asked at meetings only)
  - 1886-1890 (Box 1)
    (separate notebooks include topics for discussion only)
  - September 26, 1894-June 10,1896 (Box 1)
    (includes constitution)
  - September 23, 1896-May 26, 1897 (Box 1)
    (also includes constitution, membership roll)
  - September 22, 1897-June 8, 1898 (Box 1)
    (also includes membership roll)
  - September 28, 1898-May 31, 1899 (Box 1)
  - June 1899-June 1900 (Box 1)
  - September 26, 1900-May 29, 1901 (Box 1)
    (also includes membership roll, printed constitution)
  - June 12, 1901-June 10, 1903 (Box 1)
  - September 30, 1903-October 24, 1906 (Box 1)
  - October 31, 1906-April 28, 1909 (Box 1)
  - October 1909-February 1912 (Box 1)
  - February 14, 1912-April 30, 1914 (Box 1)
  - October 14, 1914-May 11, 1920 (Box 1)
    (also includes membership roll and clippings)
  - October 13, 1920-March 15, 1930 (Box 1)
    (also includes regulations governing the Student Loan fund, constitution of the Ypsilanti Federation of Women's Clubs, score sheet for cities)
  - March 27, 1930-May 12, 1937 (Box 1)
  - May 12, 1937-April 14, 1943 (Box 1)
  - April 28, 1943-May 18, 1949 (Box 1)
    (also includes executive board meetings (September 1945-May 1949)
  - August 1949-May 1956 (Box 1)
    (also included executive board meetings, programs, reports and several tributes to departed members)
  - October 2, 1956-January 11, 1961 (Box 2)
    (also includes executive board meetings, and miscellaneous treasury reports)
  - January 25, 1961-November 13, 1968 (Box 2)
    (also includes business meetings, executive board meetings, various financial reports)
  - July 2, 1964-September 25, 1985 (Box 2)
    (includes only advisory board, executive board, and various treasury reports)
  - January 1969-May 1978 (Box 2)
  - May 10, 1978-January 11, 1989 (Box 2)
  - 1989-1999 (Box 2)
  - 1985-2000 (Box 2)
  - 1996-2001 (Box 2)
  - 1989-2005 (Box 2)
- Board of Trustees
  The Board of Trustees file contains materials relating to the Board of Trustees from 1937 to 1973. The Board of Trustees was formed in 1914 in order to purchase club house property. This series includes a file from the papers of Mrs. P. E. (Lulu Carpenter.) Skinner who served on this board from 1953 to 1954.
  - 1937-1954 (Box 2)
    (miscellaneous reports received)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 2)
    (compiled from records of Mrs. P. E. Skinner)
  - 1950-1962 (notebook) (Box 2)
  - 1967-1973 (Box 2)
    (miscellaneous financial reports and papers)
- Annual Membership and Program Books
  Although an incomplete series, the membership and program books for the LLC run from 1910 to 1980. Each year lists officers, committees, the members and their addresses. Later books included the telephone numbers of the members and still later books added the year each member joined the organization. Printed also in this annual booklet is the monthly program schedule. In the early years, these books contained the constitution but in later years (1935, 1966, 1980) constitution booklets were published separately. Earlier constitutions can be found in the Regular Meeting Minute Books for Sept. 1894, Sept. 1900, June, 1901 and Sept. 1903.
  - 1910-1936 (incomplete) (Box 2)
  - 1936-1982 (incomplete) (Box 2)
- Financial Records
  The financial records series is made up of two subseries. Record books list members, dues and expenses from 1909 until 1941. Also included here is a much smaller book and miscellaneous papers outlining the meeting of the first financial committee in December of 1913 and notes on the purchase of the clubhouse in 1914. Miscellaneous treasurer's reports from 1900 until 1928 and treasury reports from 1937 to 1963 complete this series.
  - Record books
    - 1909-1929 (Box 3)
      members, dues, expenses
    - 1913-1914 (Box 3)
      (first financial committee meeting, notes on home purchase)
    - 1930-1941 (Box 3)
      expenses and dues
  - Treasurer's Reports
    - 1900-1928 (incomplete) (Box 3)
    - 1937-1949 (incomplete) (Box 3)
    - 1949-1959 (Box 3)
    - 1959-1963 (Box 3)
- Presidents Files
  The Presidents Files series includes several notebooks of the past Presidents containing preparations and notes for presiding over regular membership meetings. The papers of Mrs. P. E. (Lulu Carpenter) Skinner which relate to her activities with the LLC are also included. In addition to being President of LLC from 1945 to 1947, Mrs. Skinner wrote historical sketches, and plays and poems which centered on the LLC. Mrs. Skinner also served on the Board of Trustees.
  - Mrs. P. E. (Lulu Carpenter) Skinner
    - Notebook 1946 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Notes 1944-1947 (Box 3)
    - Programs, letters, miscellaneous 1941-1954 (Box 3)
    - Plays and poems (Box 3)
  - Mrs. Mildred Harris 1966-1968, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Mary Ellen Wiedman 1968-1970, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - President's Notebook 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    Josephine Calkins, Phyllis Clark, Joan Willoughby
- History of Building Addition
  The History of Building Addition series relates to the work done in 1971 and 1972 to renovate and enlarge the clubhouse of this organization.
  - Minutes of building committee 1970-1974 (Box 3)
  - General 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - General 1972-1974, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Ladies Literary Club Magazine
  The Ladies Literary Club Magazine series contains three issues dated 1903, 1904, 1912. These periodicals contain not only handwritten or typed essays, poems and travel stories but also photographs, postcards and clippings.
  - 1903-1904 (Box 3)
  - 1904 (Box 3)
  - 1912 (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks
  Twelve scrapbooks dated from 1912 to 1990 detail the interests of the organization and changes made in its activities throughout its history. The earlier scrapbooks contain mostly clippings. However over the years the content of the scrapbooks expanded to include photos, program books and other mementos relating to the activities of the organization.
  - 1912 (Box 4)
    program books, miscellaneous
  - 1927-1938 (Box 4)
    (miscellaneous photographs, 1929, handwritten Report of the Year, many typed meeting reviews)
  - 1933-1934 (Box 4)
  - 1943-1951 (Box 4)
    (also various programs)
  - 1945-1947 (Box 4)
    (also one photograph of Eunice Smith)
  - 1947-1951 (Box 4)
    (also includes some programs)
  - 1951-1953 (Box 4)
    (handwritten summary of club activities, annual program books, individual programs)
  - 1956-1961 (Box 4)
    (also annual program books)
  - 1961-1966 (programs) (Box 7)
  - 1966-1973 (Box 5)
    (program books, programs, momentos)
  - 1973-1978 (Box 6)
    (photographs, programs, miscellaneous)
  - 1978-1990 (photographs, miscellaneous.) (Box 5)
  - 1990-1995 (photographs, miscellaneous.) (Box 7)
  - 1995-2004 (photographs, miscellaneous.) (Box 6)
  - 2004-2008 (photographs, miscellaneous.) (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  The final miscellaneous series includes clippings, insurance papers, miscellaneous papers, various programs, and poetry and plays written by members.
  - Clippings (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous papers, letters, speeches photographs (Box 5)
  - Insurance papers 1955-1959 (Box 5)
  - Various event programs (Box 5)
  - Plays and Poems written by members (Box 5)